Chapter 116.
The dying whale.
Not seldom in this life, when on the right side fortune's favorites sail
close by us, we though all a droop before, catch somewhat of the rushing
breeze, and joyfully feel our bagging sails fill out. So seemed it with the
Peekquad, for next day, after encountering the gay bachelor, whales
were seen, and four were slain, and one of them by Ahab.
It was far down the afternoon, and when all these spearings of the crimson fight
were done, and floating in the lovely sunset sea and sky, sun and whale both
stillly died together, then such a sweetness and such plaintiffness, such
inreathing or curled up in that rosy air, that it almost seemed as if far
over from the deep green convent valleys of the Manila Isles, the Spanish land
breeze wantingly turned sailor had gone to sea, frighted with these vesper hymns.
Soothed again, but only soothed to deeper gloom, Ahab, who had sterned off
from the whale, sat intently watching his final wanings from the now tranquil
boat. For that strange spectacle observable in all sperm whales dying,
the turning sunwards of the head and so expiring, that strange spectacle beheld
of such a placid evening somehow to Ahab conveyed a wondrousness unknown before.
He turns and turns him to it. How slowly but how steadfastly his homage rendering
and invoking brow with his last dying motions. He too worships fire, most
faithful, broad peronial vassel of the sun. Oh, that these two favoring eyes
should see these two favoring sights.
Look here far waterloed beyond all hum of human wheel or woe in these most
candid and impartial seas where to traditions no rocks furnish tablets
where for long Chinese ages the billows have still rolled on speechless and
unspoken to as stars that shine upon the niger's unknown source. Here too life
dies sunwards full of faith. But see, no sooner dead than death whirls round the
corpse, and it heads some other way.
Oh, thou dark Hindu half of nature, who of drowned bones hast builded thy
separate throne somewhere in the heart of these unverured seas. Thou art an
infidel, thou queen, and too truly speakest to me in the wide slaughtering
typhoon, and the hushed burial of its after calm. Nor has this thy whale
sunwards turned his dying head, and then gone round again without a lesson to me.
Oh, trebly hooped and welded hip of power. Oh high aspiring rainbowed jet
that one strivest this one jettest all in vain in vain oh whale dust thou seek
intercedings with yan all quickening sun that only calls forth life but gives it
not again yet dust thou darker hath rock me with a prouder if a darker faith all
thy unnameable imminglings float beneath me here I am boyed by breath Deaths of
once living things exhaled as air but water now. Then hail forever hail O sea
in whose eternal tossings the wild fowl finds his only rest. Born of earth yet
suckled by the sea. Though hill and valley motherthered me, you billows are my foster brothers.